Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna.
We're now starting the 5th class.
We're going to start this class
from the Sanskrit as we've been doing.
They say, by tradition,
that when you become an enlightened being,
you always speak Sanskrit,
and other people hear their own language.
sarva bhuta ruta jnyanam, Yoga Sutra.
People hear their own language.
This also happened with Jesus, I think,
where people would hear their
own language when he spoke.
So it's traditional to cover some Sanskrit
just to put a seed in your mind.
So this whole class is going
to be about the question of Tim
and Tim's, apostrophe S, me and mine.
I don't know, when I was growing up,
there was this song "I, Me, Mine."
And it's kind of important for this class.
The idea of me and mine.
Misunderstanding who is Michael
and what belongs to Michael
is the source of all trouble.
In the end, it's the source
of international competition,
corporate competition, war,
personal conflict.
It all comes from a
misunderstanding of who is me
and what is mine, what belongs to me.
And we're all deeply invested in me
even at the cost of ignoring others.
And we all do that.
I don't think anyone
can claim to really care
more about someone else
than themselves in the end.
So, we are by nature selfish creatures.
And that's not exactly the problem.
But that's a manifestation
of a deeper problem,
that we don't understand who is Michael,
and what belongs to Michael.
And if we could fix that,
then the selfishness would
be fixed automatically.
And then there would
be peace in the world.
So, Nagarjuna, Arya Nagarjuna
wants to start with the
question of me and mine.
And again 'arya' itself
is a Sanskrit word.
It was misused by the Nazis to mean
superior race or something like that.
It's an old Sanskrit word
which means specifically someone
who has perceived emptiness
directly, which is very rare.
Maybe once every 500 years or something.
So, Arya Nagarjuna, sometimes
he's called just the Arya,
because I would say he's the most
famous arya of all time, in our world,
in our history, in the
last couple thousand years.
He's the one who stands out
as an extraordinary arya.
So, here's some words
that he's going to use
a lot in this class. And
I thought, it would be
good luck for us to go
through the Sanskrit.
When you go through Sanskrit,
it's called a generative language
which means it acts
according to certain rules.
There are 800 roots.
If you know the roots,
and you know the rules,
you can speak Sanskrit
and write Sanskrit without
ever seeing Sanskrit
because the rules are perfect.
It's a perfect, Sanskrit
means 'the perfect language.'
Sanskrta means 'the perfect language.'
And it means
you could predict the whole language
just from the 800 roots
because it's perfect.
All forms are perfect.
So we're going to go through...
When you discuss Sanskrit words,
it's fun to look at the root.
It's fun to see how it's generated,
how the word is generated.
And then all Western languages,
from Iceland to Iran, come from Sanskrit.
So, kick out the Semetic
languages, like Hebrew or Arabic.
Kick out Chinese, and I don't know,
Alaskan, Navajo, or something.
The rest of the world's languages
come directly from Sanskrit.
And Latin and Greek were
derived from Sanskrit.
English is basically
So when you want to
understand a Sanskrit word,
it's fun to look at the cognate.
Cognate means give me some English words
that come from this root.
And I always tell people,
if you really were into it,
you can pick up the New York Times,
and see the Sanskrit, which
is kind of a fun exercise.
You can see the whole page of
Sanskrit that it came from.
So, let's try that.
The first word I'd like
to cover is 'aham',
which is a-h-a-m.
And it's the Sanskrit word
for 'me', 'I'. And the Tibetan is 'nga.'
By the way, Tibetan is
totally off the charts.
No linguistic connection to
any language in the world.
There's a tradition, that
it came from outer space
or higher beings.
[GMR laughing]
Linguistically, it's believable
because there's not a
single word connected
to any other language.
But anyways, aham means me.
And it's the root of the word 'ego'.
H and Gs are pretty much interchangeable,
and As normally become E in English.
So the word 'ego' comes from 'aham.'
So that means 'me' in Sanskrit.
Probably 'me' comes from 'aham'.
And then 'nga yi ba' in Tibetan,
means 'mama' in Sanskrit,
and 'mama' means mine.
So aham means 'me', and mama means 'mine'.
And that's going to be important for us.
You can obviously see how the word 'me'
and the word 'mine' are cognates that
come from the word 'mama.'
Then there is an important new word
made from both of these two
words with the root √kr̩.
And the root √kr̩ which
is k-i-r in pronunciation
means to make something.
And we have the word
'karma', comes from that,
because karma makes the world.
English cognates for √kr̩ are 'cereal,'
which is the grain, which
is made by the earth.
The C used to be K,
and then K changed to an S sound.
After... Just before
Shakespeare or something.
A lot of Cs became, like 'city,'
changed from K sound to S sound.
So √kr̩ and 'create' comes from that,
with the same C.
So, I want to talk about
ahamkāra and mamakāra.
Ahaṃkāra and mamakāra.
So if you connect 'me' to 'kāra,'
it's 'making me.'
You're running around making me.
And 'mamakāra' means you're running around
making my, mine.
So 'ahaṃkāra' means 'making me',
and 'mamakāra' means 'making mine'.
And that's an important
idea to think about.
That you are running around the world,
you are defining me, and
you are defining mine.
And the way you do it so sloppily
causes a lot of conflicts in the world.
People start disagreeing
about whose is mine
and which is not mine.
All right?
The 'm' in 'aham' changes to n before k.
So you wouldn't say 'ahaṃkāra,'
you would say '[ahang kara]. Try it.
Ahaṃkāra [ahang kara],
ahaṃkāra [ahang kara].
And that long ā is ah instead of a.
So ahaṃ kāra, ahaṃ kāra, say, ahaṃ kāra
Then 'mamakāra' is easy, mamakāra.
All right,
the real, correct translation
is NGAR 'DZIN,
and NGA YIR 'DZIN
NGAR 'DZIN, which means to grab on to me,
and then NGA YI BA 'DZIN,
which means to grab on to mine.
So these are two emotions
that we all have,
that are the root of
trouble in this world.
If people could remove this ahaṃkāra
and this mamakāra,
then the world would be a beautiful place.
What do you call a beautiful
place, world in Sanskrit?
Mandala.
And the Spanish word 'mundo'
comes from the same root,
means the world.
It actually means a 'disc.'
That's a long story, but...
A perfect world, a
perfect mundo is mandala.
There are some... I
enjoy going to churches,
I enjoy going to ashrams.
I spent 10 years going to one ashram
where they teach Hindu philosophy.
And I used to go there and listen,
and I recall that they had an ahaṃkāra
in the Sankya school.
So this is one of the most
important schools of Hinduism.
Probably the main school of
the ancient traditional
yoga schools is Sankya.
They have this idea
about ahaṃkāra, which...
You see, Buddhism was prevalent
in India for a 1,000 years,
and then it died out.
It waned, and then it came back again.
And when Buddhism was collapsing,
a lot of the words got
borrowed by other traditions.
And then they took on some
really weird meanings.
So, this ahaṃkāra is a good example.
Grabbing on to me and grabbing on to mine.
I'll give you the
definition from the internet
which is always a trustworthy source.
The ahaṃkāra are a mysterious
and powerful species
of shape shifting, wish granting creatures
that first appeared in the solar system
after the traveler arrived.
So, these very basic, important,
beautiful, precious ideas about who am I,
they got totally weirded out in India.
So why I'm saying that is not
to criticize other traditions,
but to encourage you to be careful.
When you are attracted to a tradition,
then try to dig into
it, try to look at it,
try to learn it carefully,
try to see if it's authentic.
And the tradition that
we're teaching today
is 2,000 years old.
It hasn't really changed
in 2,000 years at all.
Which is why I can sit
and teach you a text
which is 2,000 years old.
The language is the same.
You ready?
Whan that Aprille with his shoures soote,
The droghte of March
hath perced to the roote,
And bathed every veyne in swich licóur
English, 500 years ago.
Chaucer.
So take Nagarjuna's 2,000
years old, four times older,
but you can easily read it.
It's a very strict tradition.
It's kept very tight.
So I encourage you not
to spend your precious,
irreplaceable life hours without checking
if a tradition is authentic.
Otherwise, you might run into
solar system traveler or something.
All right.
We've reached an interesting point.
He says, look, we discussed Tim,
and we discussed Tim's.
But how do you use that in your real life?
Come on, let's get real.
And Nagarjuna is sensitive
enough to the student,
that he doesn't just keep
pouring philosophy on your head.
He'll say, now he pauses and he says,
"How are we going to use that?"
How is that supposed to improve your life
for you to understand about me and mine?
How's that going to improve your life?
And then we have the next section here.
It starts here.
,BDAG DANG BDAG GI ZHI BA'I PHYIR,
,NGAR 'DZIN NGA YIR 'DZIN MED 'GYUR,
,NGA DANG NGA YIR 'DZIN MED GANG,
,DE YANG YOD PA MA YIN TE,
,NGAR 'DZIN NGAR YIR 'DZIN MED PAR,
,GANG GIS MTHONG BAS MI MTHONG NGO,
I'm going to read these
two paragraphs verbatim,
because the two paragraphs
have explanation.
Because I think they're very beautiful.
NGA DANG NGAR 'DZIN GYI YUL
BDAG DANG BDAG GI BA'I MTSAN MA
NYE BAR ZHI BA'I PHYIR
Your idea of who you are,
and your idea of what
belongs to you will melt
when you truly understand
the contradictions
of how you think about yourself.
ZHI BA'I PHYIR RNAL 'BYOR PAS
NGA RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PAR 'DZIN PA DANG
So, what does a RNAL 'BYOR PA do?
What's the Sanskrit, Tim? RNAL 'BYOR
Yogi.
So really in the old days,
yogi meant a person
who understood reality.
And in Tibetan, the word is
'the person who applies
their meditation perfectly',
it's the translation of the Sanskrit yogi.
So, how does a great meditator
view me and mine?
NGA RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PAR 'DZIN PA DANG
NGA YI BA RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PAR
'DZIN PA'I 'JIG LTA SPANGS
They have eliminated a misunderstanding
of who is me and what is mine.
I think it's easier if
you start with mine.
Things that are mine.
And I don't know.
When you pick up this green bottle
that we talked about before,
we instinctively feel
with our deepest instincts
that it's coming from itself.
That the bottle is
presenting itself to me,
and it's appearing to me.
And no matter how many
times you talk about it,
it's an almost unstoppable
habit of human beings
and all sentient creatures to believe
that things are coming at them.
Like if I hold up this green bottle,
you wouldn't say, "Oh dang, I
should've made a red bottle."
You don't assume that the
bottle is coming from you.
You think, "Oh this
bottle came on a truck,
"it was made in a factory.
They got the water, they poured it in."
But if you really understand Nagarjuna,
the bottle did come from you,
and the bottle is coming from you,
and the green color is coming from you.
All of these are... And by the way,
if your meditation gets really good,
you can catch yourself making it green.
If your meditation gets
really, really good,
you can watch yourself,
your mind painting it green.
Then you're like, "Oh my gosh,
then all the troubles in my
life are coming from me."
And then you become a
much more pleasant person,
because you don't blame
anybody else for your problems.
It doesn't mean your problems go away,
but it means that whole persona
of a person who blames
the world for things,
even bad drivers, stuff
like that, disappears.
You don't blame other people for stuff,
because you know it's coming from you.
And just imagine if you got
that part of your mind back,
if you got that much of your mind back,
the part of your mind which is blaming
other people and things for life.
If you got that time back,
how would you change?
And how would your attitudes
towards people change?
How often could you get upset
if you knew, all the crap
in the world was exact,
was precisely produced by your own mind?
Then you would just fix your mind.
You would focus on that, and already
you'd be incredibly happier person.
You'd be a much more pleasant person.
So anyway,
RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PAR 'DZIN PA'I
So he's talking about a yogi
who has overcome the feeling that things
are not coming from them
and they understand that
things are coming from them.
For example, Tim is coming from Tim.
And Tim was not a name put by
his mom on his body and mind.
His body, the way his body acts,
the way his mind acts,
are coming from seeds in his own mind.
And he could adjust his
body and mind infinitely.
If that's true.
NGA YI BA RANG BZHIN
GYIS GRUB PAR 'DZIN PA'I
'JIG LTA SPANGS NAS
So let's suppose you
have overcome the habit,
the natural instinct that
things are coming this way.
And suddenly you understand that
they're flowing out of your mind.
You are making pictures,
and then you're giving them names.
By the way, it doesn't
mean they're not real.
I used to teach this in
New York. She was there.
I'd say to a student... They'd
say, "Oh, nothing's real."
I'd say, "Go out, and
stand in front of a taxi
on 5th avenue. Tell me what happens."
You'd break your leg,
and you'd get a not real hospital bill.
And you'd stay on a not real hospital bed.
They'd put a not real
cast on your not real leg.
It's real, but it's coming from you.
Which is cool because it's real,
but it's adjustable by personal effort.
All right.
'JIG LTA GNYIS KYI ZHEN
YUL MED PAR RTOGS PA'I
YANG DAG PA'I DON LA ZHUGS PA'I PHYIR
So, they have overcome their habit
of misunderstanding themselves,
where they come from, and
where the world comes from.
You got this picture here?
I don't know, it's a girl
with a book, I think,
a young lady with a book.
Yes.
I saw this pictures I said
I've got to use this picture.
She's like meditating.
And what you're supposed to meditate on,
when you try to meditate on emptiness,
is to try to understand the emptiness
not of unrelated things,
but the emptiness of you,
and the emptiness of mine.
The things that are your
personal possessions.
Things that you own.
So, I thought it's a perfect picture.
Because you can imagine, she's
meditating on who is she,
where did she come from?
And she's meditating on where
her possessions came from.
And the book... I imagine
the book is by Nagarjuna,
who's telling her where
the book came from.
Anyway.
DE DAG DANG DE LAS
GZHAN PA'I NGAR 'DZIN PA
DANG NGA YIR 'DZIN PA MED CING SPONG BA
GANG YIN PA'I RNAL 'BYOR
PA DE YANG NGO BO NYID
KYIS YOD PA MA YIN TE,
But then he says,
"Let's consider the person
who understands me and mine."
Now don't focus on how
they understand themselves,
and don't focus on how they understand
the things that they own.
Focus on the person who understands, okay?
Lets see if we can understand the person
who understands themselves
and what they own.
GANG GIS NGAR 'DZIN PA
DANG NGA YIR 'DZIN PA
MED PAR SPONG BA'I RNAL 'BYOR PA
NGO BOS YOD DO SNYAM DU MTHONG BA STE
If you believe that that
person comes from themselves,
if you believe that that
person is coming from them,
so you are observing a
person who understands
who they are and where
their stuff is coming from.
But now you're observing that person,
and if you think NGO BOS YOD DO SNYAM DU,
if you think they are
coming from their selves,
if you look at them and think
that the yogi is coming from themselves,
if you look at the person
who understands me and mine,
and you get the feeling that
they must be coming then from themselves.
If you look at it that way, he says,
if you see it that way - MTHONG STE
MTHONG, like MTHONG LAM,
right JB?
DE KHO NA NYID KYI DON MI MTHONG
Then we can say you don't see anything.
It's very cute.
If you think you could lay your eyes
on a person who
understands all this stuff,
you don't see nothing.
Then Nagarjuna's really rubbing it in.
- Hey, did you ever meet a person
who understood me and mine?
- Oh yes. - Yes? Did you look at them?
- Yes. - Yes? Well, you didn't.
He's like that. He gets very frustrating.
And this gets into...
By the way, we're going to go to there,
we're going to go directly
to the Diamond Cutter Sutra.
The emptiness of the Diamond Cutter Sutra.
And I like to tell my students in Asia
who are very devoted to the
Diamond Cutter Sutra as I am,
"Who wrote it?
You did."
And when you read the Bible, or you see
"Gone With The Wind,"
according to these ideas,
you made them. You made them.
You made "Gone With The Wind."
You're the director.
Every time you turn a page in the gospel,
your mind is laying down
the words one by one.
And it's so quick that
you don't notice it.
And you don't see it.
But you are actually... you are the author
of your own salvation.
You are the one who's
writing the religious book
that finally calls to you
and pulls you out of this problem.
And it's a cool idea.
God comes from you. Jesus comes from you.
Buddha comes from you.
How can I create a being
who knows so much more than me,
that they can pull me out of trouble?
That's the cool thing
because karma escalates.
Karma tends to multiply on its own.
A small understanding can become a...
If it's well-handled,
a small understanding can
become a blanket understanding
of the whole universe.
And these diving things, angels, God,
Jesus, Mohammed, Buddha,
they're all coming from you.
If you live in a world
where these people walked
you're the one who brought them here.
And that's cool. And if you think not,
then you don't understand
what they were talking about.
That's beautiful too, right?
So anyway, that's the point
that Nagarjuna's making.
Here's the boy.
I put "Those who see, do not."
That's the theme.
This theme in Buddhism is
called "Those who see, do not."
Those who believe that the people
who came into this world to teach
the deepest things - like Jesus,
like Buddha, like Mohammed -
if they believe those
people came into this world,
and didn't come from us,
then they have never met those people.
It's very interesting.
If you think that's where
these people came from,
then you don't understand
what they're trying to tell you:
that you can be perfected,
that you can make yourself perfected.
All right.
Next verse.
,NANG DANG PHYI ROL NYID DAG LA,
,BDAG DANG BDAG GI SNYAM ZAD NA,
,NYE BAR LEN PA 'GAG 'GYUR ZHING,
,DE ZAD PAS NA SKYE BA ZAD,
He's starting to get into
practical applications.
The important word here is NYE BAR LEN PA.
Which one is it in the
Sanskrit, Christina?
It means to take something.
It should start with upa.
[Indistinct]
No, I don't think so.
I think it's the upādānaṃ, yes, upādānaṃ.
NYE BAR LEN PA
means to take something on.
And it's going to be
crucial to this verse.
The most classic reference of this word is
what happens to your body
and mind when you're born:
you take it on.
You assume a body
and you assume a mind when you're born.
So he says here, "You
can stop your grasping,
"or you can stop your grabbing,
"if you understand that me
and mine are coming from you
"and not from the outside."
Then you can stop grasping to things.
And it's kind of obvious
in the sense of money.
I don't know, my life, my relationship
with money has changed.
I didn't have any money when I was a kid.
We were even getting
food from the food bank.
And then I was brought up
in a culture that said,
"Don't focus on money."
I was brought up in the
God-bless hippie culture,
which said you are not defined
by how much money you make.
So I kind of avoided
money for a long time.
Then John Brady's project got in trouble.
We were borrowing money all the time
to save the ancient books.
And I was thinking, well maybe I should
use the philosophy to make some money.
So I did.
And the diamond company we built
is now the largest in the world.
And was brought by Warren Buffet in 2009.
And I think it's useful to have money
because you can use it.
And we support hundreds of poor people,
hundreds and hundreds of refugees.
We have 532 kids in our
school which we've built.
We feed them. We clothe them.
And his project costs
millions of dollars every few years.
Although, he doesn't
take a salary properly.
But why am I talking about that?
The idea of grasping to money,
NYE BAR LEN PA,
the idea of grasping,
that's not what it means.
So it doesn't mean if you are wealthy,
or if you know how to acquire money
and use money that you're a bad person.
It doesn't mean that.
And Buddha never meant that.
So here's the word of grabbing
that people misunderstand.
It says, "Don't grab,"
but it doesn't mean money.
In fact, it means the opposite.
If you were grabbing to money,
if you didn't understand
where money was coming from,
if you want it a lot more quickly,
you would have to hurt someone
or rob somebody to get
it. You see what I mean?
If you thought money
was not coming from you,
and you thought money was coming this way,
then automatically you'd be vulnerable
to hurting people to get money.
Because that's the only way
you can get a lot of money quick
if you had to support John's project.
But if you understood that
money is flowing from you,
like this other green...
[clanking water bottle]
If you understood it was flowing from you,
then you could easily plant money.
And it would be an interesting test
to make the largest diamond
company in the world,
to see if your ideas are correct.
Be sort of a laboratory, you see?
So why are we talking about that?
In this verse Nagarjuna is talking about
the idea of grabbing.
NYE BAR LEN PA.
Upādānaṃ.
Is the name correct, did you look it up?
Yes, upādānaṃ.
So grabbing to things.
And he says, "You know,
if you really understand
"that things are flowing from you,
it's going to protect you
forever from grabbing."
Then you don't get angry,
you don't get selfish,
you don't hurt people to
get the things you want.
You just create them, and they come,
and you make more money,
and you give it away,
and you make more.
And it's fun. It's kind of a fun,
it's fun to prove day by day
that these ideas are correct
with such a normal thing as money.
So I wanted to talk about...
He says the people who understand
the real nature of me and mine,
they overcome grabbing to things
in the sense of thinking
or feeling that money comes from itself.
Well, that the green bottle
is coming from itself.
So they overcome grabbing.
And then Choney Lama, he's kind of cute.
He says, "Hey, you know,
there's four classic grabbings.
You want to know what they are?"
And we're like, "Yes, sure, Choney Lama.
Tell us what are the
four kinds of grabbing?"
And I thought it'd be cute
if I gave them to you.
And what's cool about having a databases
of 16 million pages -
which is our 35th anniversary
this month, of inputting -
you can just ask the computer
what's the four kinds of grabbing.
And it tells you in exactly
nine seconds or something.
I used to flip through
the books page by page.
That would take about a
week to find this answer.
Now we can do it in about
less than 10 seconds.
So we can search 16 million pages
in less than 10 seconds.
As long as we stick to the input code
created by grandpa, otherwise
it will take quite a while.
Anyway, here we go.
I thought you'd like to know the four.
First one,
YUL YID 'ONG LA LHAG PAR
CHAGS PA'I 'DOD CHAGS DANG PO
Common grabbing,
which is the pursuit of desirable objects.
That's called 'common grabbing.'
Plain old grabbing. It's the
pursuit of desirable objects.
Is it wrong?
Not if you do it the right way.
Money's helpful.
He spent $15 million dollars.
He's expensive. And we wouldn't
have the 16 million pages.
So money can be used.
Anyways, but this means
wrong kind of attachment
to pleasurable objects.
First kind of grabbing, grabbingness.
Should we translate it that
way, Tim, grabbingness?
By the way, Tim, this
explanation comes from your book.
I just thought you'd like to know.
So Tim... I chose 10 translators.
I said if anyone shows that
they're really serious,
I'll take a new one.
It took five years, and then
he proved he was serious.
So about a couple of months ago
he decided he will translate something
which is a big commitment for me.
It's a 10-15 year commitment.
His book is called "The
Perfection of Wisdom,"
which is really Middle Way school.
And this is from your book.
I just thought you'd like to know.
Second one:
LTA NGAN LA LHAG PAR CHAGS PA'I 'DOD CHAGS
Second kind of grabbing is
grabbing to unhelpful ideas,
hurting people, ideas that hurt people.
And I would say one of
the big ones in this world
is competitiveness between companies,
between people, between countries,
inside of companies, between employees.
And it's this sick idea.
It's a very sick idea
that I can improve my life
if I make your life worse.
Or that we should compete for resources.
And by the way, that's the
way not to get resources.
The smartest way to not
get the resources you need
would be to compete with someone
else to get more from them.
Then that would assure that
you will be short of resources
later, if these ideas are correct.
Then the opposite, sharing resources,
would be the way to increase
the market of resources.
Those countries which share oil
and natural gas will have
more oil and natural gas
discovered in their country.
And there's a beautiful story about that
how we discovered
natural gas in shale oil.
Fracking?
That's a long story.
LTA NGAN LA LHAG
So, attachment to these sick views.
I would call them sick viewpoints.
I can get more money.
Zero sum game.
I get more pizza.
There's only eight pieces of pizza.
And if I don't take one from you,
there won't be more for me.
Instead of the idea of
buying a second pizza,
which is what Buddhism would say.
If you buy infinite number of pizzas,
maybe there'll be enough
pieces for everybody.
Third stupid view is to believe in a self
or a me, and now you know me means a thing
which is not coming from you.
Does the phone have a me?
Depends on how you look at it.
If you think the phone didn't
come from sharing phones,
then you are grabbing
to a me of the phone.
If you think that you always
get a phone by sharing phones...
I didn't pay for this
phone. Just keeps coming.
I didn't pay for the
computer, They just come.
So if you are generous,
and you help others
with the right understanding
of me and mine,
they tend to flow back.
Well, they inevitably flow back.
Okay, the fourth one.
BRTUL ZHUGS NGAN PA LA LHAG PAR CHAGS PA
This is a special kind of grabbing
that Buddha was particularly offended by
which was religious practices
which would hurt people.
So in his time, for example,
sacrifice of cows, bulls was common.
Gandhi-ji talks about it.
One of the heaviest moments in his life
was when he observed an
animal sacrificed in Varanasi.
And it changed his life.
So this idea of religion being...
that religious practices that focus on
hurting other people or
hurting other creatures,
would be religious, is the
fourth kind of grabbing.
So those are the four kinds of grabbings.
We covered Choney Lama.
I've got something here for you a picture.
I don't remember the picture.
So, I don't know, I thought
this was a cool picture for grabbing.
And they're grabbing.
And by the way... Yes, okay.
Let's go onto the next verse.
I'll read the verse.
LAS DANG...
Christina, you have the verse?
You want to do the Sanskrit for fun?
Go slow, go super slow.
And pronounce it correctly.
Loud.
- [Christina] Karmakleśakṣayān
mokṣaḥ
- [GMR] h
- [Christina] Mokṣaḥ?
- [GMR] Mokṣaḥ
- [Christina] karmakleśā vikalpataḥ
- [GMR] h, kalpataḥ
- [Christina] kalpataḥ
- [GMR] Yes, if you say "ta
ha", you ruin the meter.
- [Christina] Te prapañcāt prapañcas tu
śūnyatāyāṃ nirudhyate
- [GMR] Nice.
,LAS DANG NYON MONGS ZAD PAS THAR,
If you want to achieve nirvana or freedom,
you're going to have to
stop your negative emotions
and the harmful actions
that those emotions inspire.
That's the first line.
First half of the Sanskrit line.
,LAS DANG NYON MONGS RNAM RTOG LAS,
Where does karma, where does it come from?
Where do negative emotions
and karma come from?
They come from RNAM RTOG,
wrong thinking.
And where does that come from is SPROS PA.
And SPROS PA is a very difficult word
that means mental constructs.
Wrong thinking comes
from mental constructs,
then leads to negative emotions
which forces you to hurt people.
I'll say it again.
Wrong thinking comes from...
What did I say?
Wrong ideas lead to negative emotions,
which cause you to hurt other people.
And the root of those is some kind of
wrong idea of where
things are coming from.
,STONG PA NYID KYIS 'GAG PAR 'GYUR,
And all of this chain reaction of trouble
is stopped when you understand emptiness.
That's the last line.
And does it remind you of
anything in the ACI courses?
[GMR laughing]
We had a quotation of a commentary
to a book by Maitreya which is called
"Uttara Tantra" which is not a tantra.
It's just a normal book
called "Higher Line",
"A Higher Line."
There was a lovely description
of the chain reaction that
causes the trouble in the world.
There was a lovely description
of the domino effect
that leads from not
understanding emptiness,
up to war,
or physical suffering, death in the world.
And I love that section.
So I went and got it
because it's based on this.
Maitreya is about 150
years after Nagarjuna.
He's talking 150 years after Nagarjuna.
So I thought we would devolve,
since we have so much extra time,
to that explanation by Maitreya.
Ultimately, by Maitreya.
Maitreya is who?
- [Christina] Next Buddha.
- The next Buddha.
Next Buddha in this world.
All right.
Very, very near, unexpectedly near.
All right,
and I went and got them for you.
Again, this is from your author, Tim,
which is why I chose him for you,
because he's so sexy.
So I'll just read it
and we'll go through it.
RGYUD BLA MA RTZA 'GREL GYI DGONGS PA
MTHAR THUG YIN TE,
Here's the ultimate
intention of the next Buddha.
BDAG 'DZIN GNYIS KYI BAG CHAGS
LA BRTEN NAS DE GNYIS SKYES,
The trouble starts when
you enter this life
with seeds in your mind
from your past life
which automatically inspire you
to think that the bottle's
coming from the bottle.
So, that's not your fault.
That was Joe. Who's Joe?
I like to call your previous life 'Joe',
I don't know what his or her name was.
But it's a joke. It's an inside joke.
I asked a good friend of mine
why is he such a good person?
And he said, "Geshe-la,
it wasn't me, it was Joe.
It was in my past life."
So, you're at a disadvantage
when you enter this life.
Because you enter this
life, according to Buddhism,
with the seeds in your
mind that automatically
make you feel instinctively that
the bottle's coming towards you,
that it came from a factory,
and it's not coming from your generosity
of offering water to other people.
Which is where it's really coming from.
But you have to re-educate your mind.
Your mind assumes because of seeds
that you carried here from your past life,
that the bottle is coming from the bottle.
And if we succeed in this life,
if we use this life correctly,
by the end of this life,
our instincts will be the opposite.
Wow, I love this Pellegrino.
I'll have to make sure to give
some water to someone today,
because I want to keep it running.
And then that's such a
pleasant way to live,
that you're thanking the
world for all that you have,
and you're aware that it
comes from your kindness.
And then that's the whole
feeling of your life
that you want to keep it going.
You want to keep being
kind to other people.
Anyway, he says, "Unfortunately,
we walk into this life
"with these negative
seeds from the past life.
"And that's why
"automatically, without thinking,
"since you came out of your mother,
"even an infant, even an ant,
is automatically thinking,
"things are coming this way.
And not left to yourself."
I like to call it... it's like
the kids I met in Mongolia.
So, I used to go to Mongolia a
lot. We have a project there.
I was trying to save 600 thousand books.
Currently saying 300 thousand books.
John's going to do that deal.
One night, coming home from the library,
I saw a sewer cover lift up,
and an animal ran past me, like a wolf.
And I was so freaked out.
Because there's no electricity enough
for lights on the streets.
And I just felt this
animal rushed past me.
And I asked this friend,
this Mongolian with me,
I said, "What is that?"
"What's that animal? What
kind of animal can lift up
a sewer cover and run down the street?"
He says, "Geshe-la, that's not animals.
Those are kids. Feral kids."
And I'm like, "What?"
And he says, "Their parents died."
And I said, "Well, what are
they doing in the sewers?"
He says, "That's the only
warm place in Mongolia.
"If you don't have any
money, you live in the sewer.
"You crawl down in the
sewer and try to stay warm,
next to the warm water."
And I'm like, "Uh!"
And he said,
"Don't get near them
Geshe-la, they'll bite you.
"They'll bite you, and
they're very dangerous.
They'll give you rabies."
And I'm like, "Whoa!
Can't you talk to them?"
He says, "They don't know language.
"They never learned language.
They didn't have parents.
They never had parents. They
are feral. They are animals."
And there's a lady who got a Nobel Prize
by trying to take care of them.
We used to help her. But anyway,
why am I saying that?
Left to yourself in this lifetime
without any other
competing thought system,
you would believe that this
was coming from itself.
And you would fight to get
them when you wanted them.
And in the end, if push came to shove...
I was in Hawaii, surfing,
when the gas thing happened,
the Oil Embargo happened,
and people were in line
to get gas every other
day. And people had guns.
And people were shooting
each other for gas.
He says, "You think you're so civilized.
"But if push came to shove,
"and it was the last bottle of water,
"and you didn't understand
that it comes from you,
you would hurt someone else to get it."
So we're feral. We're born feral,
because of our last life.
We come into this life thinking
that the water is there, and
that it's not coming from
how I treat other people.
We are feral by nature, number one.
Two. Then you start to believe that
the thing exists out there.
Due to the seeds in your last life
you start to believe that
things exist out there,
and that they're coming this way.
Then your seed, what do you call it,
your selection of seeds in your mind
makes you perceive some
things as desirable
and some things as undesirable.
Like this is nice water.
I don't personally like LaCroix water.
So that's also your seeds operating.
Due to that, comes up...
This water looks good to me.
That canned water doesn't look good to me.
Due to those two misperceptions,
thinking that the water comes this way,
I start to want one,
and not want the other.
That's a natural reaction.
When one water looks nice,
and the other water doesn't look nice,
I would rather have the
one that looks nice to me.
So then you get this thing
called liking and disliking.
What do we call it?
Ignorant liking and ignorant disliking.
And that triggers karma. Why?
You fight for the things you want.
You fight to get away from
the things you don't want.
And that's karma. That creates karma.
Due to that, you plant
seeds for next time.
So then it starts to become a cycle.
So what Nagarjuna's
explaining in this verse
is that same cycle.
If you never figure out that
things are coming from you,
you will repeat.
What do you call it?
Reboot. Repeat.
You'll just keep going like this and this.
Your life will continue
to be a downward spiral,
and it will end in the
inevitable death and poverty,
the ultimate poverty where
you even don't own your body.
So anyway, he's saying
that's the typical cycle.
Can we break it?
Can you break it? That's
coming up in the next class,
which you have to come to
if you want to know how to break it.
Okay, see you then.